<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="a">A New Epoch in the Study of Medieval Karaite Grammatical Theory / עידן חדש בחקר תורת הדקדוק של הקראים</title><title level="j">Lĕšonénu: A Journal for the Study of the Hebrew Language and Cognate Subjects / לשוננו: כתב-עת לחקר הלשון העברית והתחומים הסמוכים לה</title><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/soas_c13">SOAS C13</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/soas_c13">SOAS C13</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority/><idno type="URI">https://majlis.net/bibl/6KKICQPW/tei</idno><date>2022-07-26-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2022-07-26-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><analytic><author><name>נאסר בסל</name></author><author><name>Nasir Basal</name></author><title level="a">A New Epoch in the Study of Medieval Karaite Grammatical Theory / עידן חדש בחקר תורת הדקדוק של הקראים</title><idno type="URI">https://majlis.net/bibl/6KKICQPW</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4419449/items/6KKICQPW</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4419449/items/6KKICQPW</idno></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Lĕšonénu: A Journal for the Study of the Hebrew Language and Cognate Subjects / לשוננו: כתב-עת לחקר הלשון העברית והתחומים הסמוכים לה</title><biblScope unit="vol">סח</biblScope><imprint><date>2006</date></imprint><biblScope unit="pp">139-159</biblScope></monogr><note type="abstract">This critical edition of the medieval Judeo-Arabic grammatical composition al-Kitāb al-Kāfī is a masterpiece, impressive not only for the quality of its scholarship but also for its handsome printing. The editor, Geoffrey Khan, one of the outstanding researchers of Judeo-Arabic culture, and his colleagues, have published the first complete edition of the composition of the greatest Karaite grammarian, 'Abū al-Faraj Hārūn, including an accurate critical apparatus, an excellent English translation, and insightful comments. A difficult, cumbersome text, scattered over multiple manuscripts in a disorderly fashion, has been transformed into a fluent, easily read and comprehensible composition. The combination of Arabic text with English translation makes 'Abū al-Faraj's work eminently accessible. Equaled by few scholarly works, it stands out as an imitation-worthy model. This edition and translation not only make a significant contribution to grammatical study – of the grammar of 'Abū al-Faraj, Karaite grammar, and Hebrew grammar in the medieval era – they also shed light on other medieval Hebrew grammatical compositions, both Karaite and Rabbanite. The comprehensive, elegantly phrased introduction in which Geoffrey Khan summarizes the scholarship on 'Abū al-Faraj and ancient Karaite grammatical theory is accompanied by a useful list of grammatical terms, an inventory of the manuscripts of al-Kitāb al-Kāfī, and an outstanding innovation: the discovery of a section of an unknown work by 'Abū al-Faraj, Kitāb al-Madxal. In sum, this volume makes an invaluable contribution to the study of medieval Hebrew grammar. It unquestionably changes current research, paves the way for subsequent scholarship, and should serve many future generations of researchers.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  נאסר בסל, and Nasir Basal. “A New Epoch in the Study of Medieval Karaite Grammatical Theory / עידן חדש בחקר תורת הדקדוק של הקראים.” <title level="m">Lĕšonénu: A Journal for the Study of the Hebrew Language and Cognate Subjects / לשוננו: כתב-עת לחקר הלשון העברית והתחומים הסמוכים לה</title> סח, no. א/ב (2006): 139–59.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Ajournal&amp;amp;rft.genre=article&amp;amp;rft.atitle=A%20New%20Epoch%20in%20the%20Study%20of%20Medieval%20Karaite%20Grammatical%20Theory%20%2F%20%D7%A2%D7%99%D7%93%D7%9F%20%D7%97%D7%93%D7%A9%20%D7%91%D7%97%D7%A7%D7%A8%20%D7%AA%D7%95%D7%A8%D7%AA%20%D7%94%D7%93%D7%A7%D7%93%D7%95%D7%A7%20%D7%A9%D7%9C%20%D7%94%D7%A7%D7%A8%D7%90%D7%99%D7%9D&amp;amp;rft.jtitle=L%C4%95%C5%A1on%C3%A9nu%3A%20A%20Journal%20for%20the%20Study%20of%20the%20Hebrew%20Language%20and%20Cognate%20Subjects%20%2F%20%D7%9C%D7%A9%D7%95%D7%A0%D7%A0%D7%95%3A%20%D7%9B%D7%AA%D7%91-%D7%A2%D7%AA%20%D7%9C%D7%97%D7%A7%D7%A8%20%D7%94%D7%9C%D7%A9%D7%95%D7%9F%20%D7%94%D7%A2%D7%91%D7%A8%D7%99%D7%AA%20%D7%95%D7%94%D7%AA%D7%97%D7%95%D7%9E%D7%99%D7%9D%20%D7%94%D7%A1%D7%9E%D7%95%D7%9B%D7%99%D7%9D%20%D7%9C%D7%94&amp;amp;rft.volume=%D7%A1%D7%97&amp;amp;rft.issue=%D7%90%2F%D7%91&amp;amp;rft.aulast=%D7%A0%D7%90%D7%A1%D7%A8%20%D7%91%D7%A1%D7%9C&amp;amp;rft.au=%D7%A0%D7%90%D7%A1%D7%A8%20%D7%91%D7%A1%D7%9C&amp;amp;rft.au=Nasir%20Basal&amp;amp;rft.date=2006&amp;amp;rft.pages=139-159&amp;amp;rft.spage=139&amp;amp;rft.epage=159&amp;amp;rft.issn=0334-3626"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">נאסר בסל and Nasir Basal, <title level="a">A New Epoch in the Study of Medieval Karaite Grammatical Theory / עידן חדש בחקר תורת הדקדוק של הקראים,</title> <title level="m">Lĕšonénu: A Journal for the Study of the Hebrew Language and Cognate Subjects / לשוננו: כתב-עת לחקר הלשון העברית והתחומים הסמוכים לה</title> סח, no. א/ב (2006): 139–59.</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>