<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="a">Exegesis' Methods of the Bible in the Dictionary of the Karaite David Ben Abraham Alfāsī, "Kitāb Jāmi' al-Alfāż" / דרכי הפרשנות למקרא במילונו של הקראי דוד בן אברהם אלפאסי, "כתאב ג'אמע אלאלפאט'"</title><title level="j">Beit Mikra: Journal for the Study of the Bible and Its World / בית מקרא: כתב-עת לחקר המקרא ועולמו</title><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/soas_c13">SOAS C13</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/lea_poralla">lea_poralla</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/soas_c13">SOAS C13</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Record edited in Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/lea_poralla">lea_poralla</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority/><idno type="URI">https://majlis.net/bibl/FM6G5JZV/tei</idno><date>2022-07-26-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2022-07-26-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><analytic><author><forename>Esther Gamliel</forename><surname>Barak</surname></author><title level="a">Exegesis' Methods of the Bible in the Dictionary of the Karaite David Ben Abraham Alfāsī, "Kitāb Jāmi' al-Alfāż" / דרכי הפרשנות למקרא במילונו של הקראי דוד בן אברהם אלפאסי, "כתאב ג'אמע אלאלפאט'"</title><idno type="URI">https://majlis.net/bibl/FM6G5JZV</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4419449/items/FM6G5JZV</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4419449/items/FM6G5JZV</idno><ref target="http://www.jstor.org/stable/24305003"/></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Beit Mikra: Journal for the Study of the Bible and Its World / בית מקרא: כתב-עת לחקר המקרא ועולמו</title><textLang mainLang="he"/><biblScope unit="vol">נט</biblScope><imprint><date>2014</date></imprint><biblScope unit="pp">76-128</biblScope></monogr><note type="abstract">[The Hebrew-Arabic Dictionary 'Kitāb Jāmi' al-Alfāż (henceforth called The Dictionary) was composed by the Karaite David Ben Abraham Alfāsī towards the end of the first half of the 10th century. The Dictionary is organized in alphabetical order and defines all Biblical words, both Hebrew and Aramaic words. The Dictionary is neither an exegesis nor a systematic grammar book: It does not explain verses in biblical order, nor does it discuss grammatical issues according to topics. However, while defining a word, Alfāsī adds linguistic and exegetical observations. Often, the need for exegesis arises when there is a contextual difficulty related to language or content. Alfāsī used the following eight methods, which are mainly linguisticcontextual methods, to explain biblical words or content: Philology, Taqdlr, Ta'wīl, Context, Heqqesh, Masorah, the Onkelos and Yonatan translations and Mishnaic and Talmudic Hebrew. Philology is the allinclusive knowledge of the language which was used by lexicographers, grammarians and exegetes before and during Alfāsī's time in order to resolve textual problems by using omitted letters, switched letters and syntactic agreement. Taqdīr is a reader's attempted theory regarding the message that is conveyed in an unclear text. Ta'wīl is an interpretive method which goes beyond the literal explanation of the text. Context means drawing conclusions from adjacent texts and Heqqesh means drawing conclusions through a comparison between non-adjacent texts. The use of Masorah as an interpretive method means explaining the text by relying on the Masorah' annotations regarding spelling and cantillation as an example. The Onkelos and Yonatan translations are early lexicons which were utilized by Alfasī to explain infrequent words or hapax legomenon. The use of several exegetical methods to explain the biblical text points to Alfāsī's strong desire to be as meticulous and as accurate as possible. Due to his background as a lexicographer and his belief that knowledge of linguistics is vital for explaining the text, he tends to offer philological solutions to difficulties in the text. He often adds the basic form of the grammatical inflection of the word and sometimes also the basic form in Aramaic after translating the word, even when no textual difficulty exists. This does not necessarily mean that Alfāsī prefers the use of Philology over other exegetical methods. On the contrary, in some texts, he rejects the philological interpretation and prefers a contextual explanation. Alafsī's preferences are therefore objective, as they are based on linguistic-interpretive reasons. Alfāsī and his contemporaries had been familiar with most of the above-mentioned exegetical methods before their appearance in his Dictionary: Rav Saadia Gaon had been familiar with many philological principles and both he and Judah Ben Quraysh had been familiar with the principles of comparing languages and using Mishnaic and Talmudic Hebrew to define Biblical words. Daniel al-Qūmisī had also known the use of Context as an exegetical method. Nevertheless, Alfāsī's main innovation was the consistent in-depth application of these known methods throughout his Dictionary. Another important innovation of Alfāsī was the use of the Masorah as an exegetical method, since until that time, such use of the Masorah had not been known. Originally, the Masorah was intended to serve as a tool to preserve the biblical text and transmit it accurately to future generations. The shift from a preserving tool to an interpretive tool was a significant change. That change was made possible only because Alfāsī had in-depth knowledge of both the Tiberian and Babylonian Masorah. Due to his extensive knowledge, Alfāsī's often had disputes with other exegetes, who in his opinion did not have sufficient understanding of the Masorah. Indeed, he stresses the importance of in-depth understanding of the Masorah as he stresses the importance of in-depth knowledge of linguistics for the purpose of understanding biblical texts and deriving legal (halachic) rulings. These were Alfasl's important innovative contributions to biblical exegesis.]</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Barak, Esther Gamliel. “Exegesis’ Methods of the Bible in the Dictionary of the Karaite David Ben Abraham Alfāsī, ‘Kitāb Jāmi’ al-Alfāż’ / דרכי הפרשנות למקרא במילונו של הקראי דוד בן אברהם אלפאסי, ‘כתאב ג’אמע אלאלפאט’.’” <title level="m">Beit Mikra: Journal for the Study of the Bible and Its World / בית מקרא: כתב-עת לחקר המקרא ועולמו</title> נט, no. ב (2014): 76–128. http://www.jstor.org/stable/24305003.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Ajournal&amp;amp;rft.genre=article&amp;amp;rft.atitle=Exegesis&amp;apos;%20Methods%20of%20the%20Bible%20in%20the%20Dictionary%20of%20the%20Karaite%20David%20Ben%20Abraham%20Alf%C4%81s%C4%AB%2C%20%22Kit%C4%81b%20J%C4%81mi&amp;apos;%20al-Alf%C4%81%C5%BC%22%20%2F%20%D7%93%D7%A8%D7%9B%D7%99%20%D7%94%D7%A4%D7%A8%D7%A9%D7%A0%D7%95%D7%AA%20%D7%9C%D7%9E%D7%A7%D7%A8%D7%90%20%D7%91%D7%9E%D7%99%D7%9C%D7%95%D7%A0%D7%95%20%D7%A9%D7%9C%20%D7%94%D7%A7%D7%A8%D7%90%D7%99%20%D7%93%D7%95%D7%93%20%D7%91%D7%9F%20%D7%90%D7%91%D7%A8%D7%94%D7%9D%20%D7%90%D7%9C%D7%A4%D7%90%D7%A1%D7%99%2C%20%22%D7%9B%D7%AA%D7%90%D7%91%20%D7%92&amp;apos;%D7%90%D7%9E%D7%A2%20%D7%90%D7%9C%D7%90%D7%9C%D7%A4%D7%90%D7%98&amp;apos;%22&amp;amp;rft.jtitle=Beit%20Mikra%3A%20Journal%20for%20the%20Study%20of%20the%20Bible%20and%20Its%20World%20%2F%20%D7%91%D7%99%D7%AA%20%D7%9E%D7%A7%D7%A8%D7%90%3A%20%D7%9B%D7%AA%D7%91-%D7%A2%D7%AA%20%D7%9C%D7%97%D7%A7%D7%A8%20%D7%94%D7%9E%D7%A7%D7%A8%D7%90%20%D7%95%D7%A2%D7%95%D7%9C%D7%9E%D7%95&amp;amp;rft.volume=%D7%A0%D7%98&amp;amp;rft.issue=%D7%91&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Esther%20Gamliel&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Barak&amp;amp;rft.au=Esther%20Gamliel%20Barak&amp;amp;rft.date=2014&amp;amp;rft.pages=76-128&amp;amp;rft.spage=76&amp;amp;rft.epage=128&amp;amp;rft.issn=0005979X&amp;amp;rft.language=he"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Esther Gamliel Barak, <title level="a">Exegesis’ Methods of the Bible in the Dictionary of the Karaite David Ben Abraham Alfāsī, ‘Kitāb Jāmi’ al-Alfāż’ / דרכי הפרשנות למקרא במילונו של הקראי דוד בן אברהם אלפאסי, ‘כתאב ג’אמע אלאלפאט’,’</title> <title level="m">Beit Mikra: Journal for the Study of the Bible and Its World / בית מקרא: כתב-עת לחקר המקרא ועולמו</title> נט, no. ב (2014): 76–128, http://www.jstor.org/stable/24305003.</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>