<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="a">Composition analysis of writing materials in Geniza fragments</title><title>Studies in Manuscript Cultures</title><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/soas_c13">SOAS C13</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/soas_c13">SOAS C13</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority/><idno type="URI">https://jalit.org/bibl/IRXM7ST6</idno><date>2022-07-26-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2022-07-26-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change><change who="mmoliere" when="2024-01-25">Updated URL to new domain name.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><analytic><author><forename>Zina</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></author><author><forename>Judith</forename><surname>Olszowy-Schlanger</surname></author><author><forename>Oliver</forename><surname>Hahn</surname></author><author><forename>Ira</forename><surname>Rabin</surname></author><title level="a">Composition analysis of writing materials in Geniza fragments</title><idno type="URI">https://jalit.org/bibl/IRXM7ST6</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4419449/items/IRXM7ST6</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4419449/items/IRXM7ST6</idno><ref target="https://www.degruyter.com/view/books/9783110546422/9783110546422-013/9783110546422-013.xml"/></analytic><monogr><editor><forename>Irina</forename><surname>Wandrey</surname></editor><title level="m">Jewish Manuscript Cultures: New Perspectives</title><textLang mainLang="en"/><imprint><pubPlace>Berlin &amp; Boston</pubPlace><publisher>Walter de Gruyter</publisher><date>2017</date></imprint></monogr><series><title>Studies in Manuscript Cultures</title><biblScope>13</biblScope></series><note type="abstract">Our current projects focus on the material analysis of the writing materials kept in the Taylor-Schechter Collection at Cambridge University Library, which houses the largest collection of Cairo Geniza fragments, about 190,000. Although Geniza manuscripts have attracted a great deal of scholarly attention, the material aspects of these documents seem to have been largely neglected. The current study aims to obtain information on the composition of the writing supports and the inks that were used, the production of the original manuscripts and the history of their degradation. The collected data should supplement the description based on Hebrew palaeography and codicology. Moreover, a characterisation of the writing materials would provide insights on trade, local production techniques and social structures. The tabulated results have the potential to be used as geo-chronological markers if sufficient data is collected. For our study, we chose Hebrew legal documents and letters from three communities that co-existed in Fustat (today Cairo) in the 11th century: the Jerusalemite (or ‘Palestinian’) community, the Babylonian community and the Karaites, three different communities with different scribal traditions. In addition to this, we studied non-biblical scrolls attributed to the Palestinian and Babylonian communities. The question we addressed was whether we can correlate the use of a specific type of ink to an objective criterion. For our analysis at Cambridge University Library, we used a number of protocols developed at BAM (Bundesanstalt für Materialforschung und -prüfung) in Berlin and at the Centre for Study of Manuscript Cultures, University of Hamburg (CSMC). These include reflectographic examination followed by non-destructive X-ray fluorescence (XRF) analysis using transportable instruments so that the analysis can be carried out in situ. We have illustrated our approach here by providing two examples. The first one describes our investigation of the leather fragment containing a portion of the Babylonian Talmud on its hair side (TS Misc.26.53.17). The second example illustrates our ability to compare iron-gall inks using the XRF method. In this case, we explored the question of the codicological attribution of three fragments (TS F17.4, TS 12.755 and TS 12.756) to the same Talmud manuscript.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Cohen, Zina, Judith Olszowy-Schlanger, Oliver Hahn, and Ira Rabin. “Composition Analysis of Writing Materials in Geniza Fragments.” In <title level="m">Jewish Manuscript Cultures: New Perspectives</title>, edited by Irina Wandrey. Studies in Manuscript Cultures 13. Berlin &amp; Boston: Walter de Gruyter, 2017. https://doi.org/10.1515/9783110546422-013.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_id=urn%3Aisbn%3A978-3-11-054642-2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Abook&amp;amp;rft.genre=bookitem&amp;amp;rft.atitle=Composition%20analysis%20of%20writing%20materials%20in%20Geniza%20fragments&amp;amp;rft.btitle=Jewish%20Manuscript%20Cultures%3A%20New%20Perspectives&amp;amp;rft.place=Berlin%20%26%20Boston&amp;amp;rft.publisher=Walter%20de%20Gruyter&amp;amp;rft.series=Studies%20in%20Manuscript%20Cultures&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Zina&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Cohen&amp;amp;rft.au=Zina%20Cohen&amp;amp;rft.au=Judith%20Olszowy-Schlanger&amp;amp;rft.au=Oliver%20Hahn&amp;amp;rft.au=Ira%20Rabin&amp;amp;rft.au=Irina%20Wandrey&amp;amp;rft.date=2017&amp;amp;rft.isbn=978-3-11-054642-2&amp;amp;rft.language=en"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Zina Cohen et al., <title level="a">Composition Analysis of Writing Materials in Geniza Fragments,</title> in <title level="m">Jewish Manuscript Cultures: New Perspectives</title>, ed. Irina Wandrey, Studies in Manuscript Cultures 13 (Berlin &amp; Boston: Walter de Gruyter, 2017), https://doi.org/10.1515/9783110546422-013.</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>