<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" xml:lang="en">Yašar ben Ḥesed ben Yašar</title>
                <title level="m" xml:lang="en">MAJLIS: The Transformation of Jewish Literature in Arabic in the Islamicate World</title>
                <sponsor ref="https://www.uni-muenchen.de">
                    <orgName>Ludwig Maximilian University of Munich</orgName>(<orgName xml:lang="de">Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München</orgName>)</sponsor>
                <sponsor ref="http://www.naher-osten.uni-muenchen.de">
                    <orgName>Institute of Near and Middle Eastern Studies</orgName>(<orgName xml:lang="de">Institut für den Nahen und Mittleren Osten</orgName>)</sponsor>
                <funder ref="https://erc.europa.eu/">
                    <orgName>ERC: European Research Council</orgName>(<orgName xml:lang="de">Europäischer Forschungsrat</orgName>)</funder>
                <principal ref="#rvollandt">Ronny Vollandt</principal>
                <editor xml:id="rvollandt" role="general" ref="https://www.naher-osten.uni-muenchen.de/personen/professoren/ronny_vollandt/index.html                         http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1702-2981                         https://viaf.org/viaf/309581349">Ronny Vollandt</editor>
                <editor role="creator" ref="#mmoliere">Maximilian de Molière</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Srophé app design and development by</resp>
                    <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
                </respStmt>
                <editor role="entry-editor">Gregor Schwarb</editor>
            <editor role="contributor">Jonathan Beise</editor>
                <editor role="contributor">Maurizio Boehm</editor><editor role="contributor">Lukas Froschmeier</editor><editor role="contributor">Annabelle Fuchs</editor><editor role="contributor">Nathan P. Gibson</editor>
                <editor role="contributor">Lea Gzella</editor><editor role="contributor">Polina Lakteikina</editor><editor role="contributor">Sara Mattutat</editor>
                <editor xml:id="mmoliere" role="contributor" ref="https://www.naher-osten.uni-muenchen.de/personen/wiss_ma/maximilian_de_moliere/index.html                         https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2168-8655                         http://viaf.org/viaf/65156495392717561393">Maximilian de Molière</editor>
                <editor role="contributor">Lea Poralla</editor><editor xml:id="gschwarb" role="contributor" ref="https://www.naher-osten.uni-muenchen.de/personen/wiss_ma/gregor_schwarb/index.html                         http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9090-1878                         https://viaf.org/viaf/90488472">Gregor Schwarb</editor>
                <editor role="contributor">Masoumeh Seydi</editor>
                <editor role="contributor">Jakob Shub-Oseledchik</editor>
                <editor role="contributor">Ezra Stadler</editor>
                <editor role="contributor">Peter Tarras</editor><editor role="contributor">Nadine Urbiczek</editor></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>
                    <ref target="https://jalit.org">jalit.org – Jewish-Arabic Literature</ref>
                </authority>
                <idno type="URI">https://jalit.org/person/15</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
                        <p>
                            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0) License.</p>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2021-10-23</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>
                    <p>Born digital.</p>
                </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="unpublished">
            <change who="#gschwarb" when="2025-06-06T04:10:15.629Z">al-Tustarī, canon. name 3</change><change who="#gschwarb" when="2025-06-04T14:39:51.900Z">Bio update al-Tustari</change>
            <change who="#gschwarb" when="2025-06-04T08:31:49.297Z">short-bio for al-Tustarī</change>
            <change who="#S.Mattutat" when="2024-12-13T14:33:16.045Z">Person: Personal Name.</change>
            <change who="#mmoliere" when="2024-09-02T13:11:10.982Z">Added heritage data.</change>
            <change who="#mmoliere" when="2024-05-08">Added bibliography from Zotero DB.</change>
            <change who="#mmoliere" when="2024-02-01">Added alternate names and identifiers.</change>
            <change who="#mmoliere" when="2024-01-29">Adapted to schema modifications.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="person-15">
                    <state>
                        <label cert="high">Author</label>
                    </state>
                    <note resp="gschwarb" type="biography" xml:lang=""><p>Sahl b. al-Faḍl b. Sahl al-Tustarī, known in Hebrew as Yašar ben Ḥesed ben Yašar, was a distinguished member of the illustrious Qaraite Jewish Tustarī family, a household that achieved considerable fame and fortune in eleventh-century Egypt. His lineage traced its origins to Tustar (or Shushtar) in the province of Ahwāz, Khūzistān, in present-day southwestern Iran. The family’s emigration to Egypt, led by his great-grandfather Isrāʾīl and his three sons in the mid- to late tenth century, marked the beginning of their prominence in the service of the Fatimid state. 
<lb/> Thanks to the fortuitous survival of documentary evidence in the Cairo Geniza, the Tustarī family is among the best-documented Jewish lineages of the medieval Islamic world. Of particular note are the careers of Sahl’s father, Abū Naṣr al-Faḍl (d. 440/1048–49), and his uncle, Abū Saʿd Ibrāhīm (d. 439/1047). These two brothers attained considerable wealth and influence during the later years of the caliph al-Ḥākim’s reign (r. 386–411/996–1021) and flourished further under his successor, al-Ẓāhir (r. c. 411–27/1021–36). Their initial entrée into court life was through their role as purveyors of rare and luxurious goods, which included the trafficking of enslaved persons—a practice then entrenched in elite commerce. 
<lb/> A notable incident underscores their proximity to power: Abū Saʿd Ibrāhīm sold to the Fatimid court an enslaved African woman named Raṣad, who would become the mother of the future caliph al-Mustanṣir. Upon her son’s accession to the throne as a child, Raṣad assumed considerable authority, and Abū Saʿd effectively functioned as a minister to her household. This position enabled him, and by extension his brother Abū Naṣr al-Faḍl, to wield significant influence at the highest levels of the state. Abū Naṣr, for his part, held a series of prominent posts, serving first as secretary to the leading Fatimid military commander in Syria, later overseeing the caliph’s private textile treasury and managing military affairs on behalf of the court. 
<lb/> In contrast to the vivid documentation of his father’s and uncle’s public roles, the life of Sahl b. al-Faḍl remains sketchy. Although fragments of his literary corpus survive – some in holograph manuscripts – and he is remarkably mentioned in a travelogue by a Muslim Andalusian scholar, many aspects of his biography remain vague. 
<lb/> Virtually nothing is known of Sahl’s birth or early upbringing. Scholars have speculated that he may have been born around 1010, but this date seems somewhat premature, given that all of his extant dated works were composed in the late 1080s and 1090s. A more plausible estimate would place his birth in the 1030s. This would align with the record of a manuscript copy of one of his works made in Tinnīs in 448/1057 and with the fact that his father died in 440/1048–49. It is possible that, as a child, he accompanied his father to Palestine when the latter was appointed secretary to the Fatimid commander Anūshtekīn in 1040. 
<lb/> Sahl undoubtedly received a traditional Qaraite education, grounded in biblical exegesis, religious law, and Muʿtazilī theology – fields in which he later made his mark as an author. He may also have benefited from maternal connections to Egypt’s Jewish elite; his mother is plausibly identified as either a daughter of the prominent merchant Yūsuf b. Yaʿqūb b. ʿAwkal or of the Qaraite notable Sahlawayh b. Ḥayyim. 
<lb/> The surviving writings of Sahl b. al-Faḍl al-Tustarī offer only a faint impression of his personal character. Nonetheless, his intellectual temperament emerges through his enduring correspondence and polemical engagements. He maintained a decades-long exchange of letters with ʿAlī b. Sulaymān al-Maqdisī. He was an outspoken critic of the marriage reforms proposed by Yešuʿa ben Yehuda (Abū l-Faraǧ Furqān b. Asad), and wrote against Saʿadya Gaon. A particularly evocative vignette of his intellectual life survives in the lone reference to him in a Muslim source: a travel account that recounts a majlis-debate in Jerusalem between Sahl and the Andalusian Mālikī jurist Abū l-Walīd al-Ṭurṭūshī. 
<lb/> Although no definitive record survives concerning Sahl’s profession, there is reason to believe that he may have served in an administrative capacity within the Fatimid state. His Muḫtaṣar fī ṣināʿat al-kitāba, a compendium of the Secretary’s Craft, hints at practical engagement with bureaucratic life and aligns with the career paths pursued by his father and other contemporaries. 
<lb/> The date of Sahl’s death remains uncertain. A Geniza letter written shortly after the Crusader conquest of Jerusalem in 1099 refers to an "Abū Saʿd, the son of al-Tustarī’s wife,” who was being held captive by the Franks. Some have interpreted this phrase as implying that Sahl had already died, but the language is ambiguous. It was not customary for adult men to be identified matrilineally unless exceptional circumstances applied, such as step-kinship or political prominence. As such, it is plausible that this Abū Saʿd was a stepson of Sahl, and that the mention of “al-Tustarī” in the passage either points to Sahl still being alive or simply reflects his enduring renown. Either way, by the time of the First Crusade, Sahl was likely either deceased or of an advanced age. 
<lb/> Sahl’s intellectual legacy comprises at least nine identifiable works. Of these, seven survive wholly or in part, some in his own handwriting. His subjects ranged from ritual and personal law to scriptural commentary and speculative theology. They point to a thinker deeply attuned to the evolving intellectual discourse of his time. He appears to have been among the earliest Jewish thinkers to incorporate Aristotelian methods into the field of legal methodology (uṣūl al-fiqh). In this respect, he stands alongside major contemporaneous Muslim intellectuals such as Imām al-Ḥaramayn al-Ǧuwaynī (d. 478/1085) and Abū Ḥāmid al-Ġazālī (d. 505/1111). Moreover, he was actively promoting the works of Abū l-Ḥusayn al-Baṣrī (d. 436/1044), who challenged key tenets of the Muʿtazilī-Bahšamī doctrine endorsed by his teachers.</p></note>
                    <persName xml:lang="ar-Latn" type="majlis-headword" xml:id="name-1">
                        <name>Abū l-Faḍl Sahl b. al-Faḍl al-Tustarī</name>
                    </persName><persName xml:lang="he-Latn" type="majlis-headword" xml:id="name-2">
                        <name>Yašar ben Ḥesed ben Yašar</name>
                    </persName>
                    
                    
                    
                    <persName type="alternate" xml:lang="he" xml:id="name-3">
                        <name source="#isni">אלתסתרי, סהל בן פצ'ל</name>
                    </persName>
                    <persName type="alternate" xml:lang="he-Latn" xml:id="name-4">
                        <name source="#isni">Tustari, sahl ben Fats'l</name>
                    </persName>
                    <persName type="canon" xml:lang="ar" xml:id="name-5">
                        
                        <addName xml:id="ku-ar" type="kunya">أبو الفضل</addName><addName xml:id="is-ar" type="ism">سهل</addName>
                        <addName xml:id="na-ar" type="nasab">بن الفضل</addName>
                        <addName xml:id="ni-ar" type="nisbah">التستري</addName>
                        
                        
                    </persName>
                    <persName type="canon" xml:lang="ar-Hebr" xml:id="name-6">
                        
                        <addName ref="#ku-ar" type="kunya">אבו אלפצ̇ל</addName><addName ref="#is-ar" type="ism">סהל</addName>
                        <addName ref="#na-ar" type="nasab">אבן אלפצ̇ל</addName>
                        <addName ref="#ni-ar" type="nisbah">אלתסתרי</addName>
                        
                        
                    </persName>
                    <persName corresp="" type="canon" xml:lang="ar-Latn" xml:id="name-7">
                        
                        <addName ref="#ku-ar" type="kunya">Abū l-Faḍl</addName><addName ref="#is-ar" type="ism">Sahl</addName>
                        <addName ref="#na-ar" type="nasab">b. al-Faḍl</addName>
                        <addName ref="#ni-ar" type="nisbah">al-Tustarī</addName>
                        
                        
                    </persName><persName type="canon" xml:lang="he" xml:id="name-8">
                        <forename xml:id="fn-he">ישר</forename>
                        <addName xml:id="pa-he" type="patronym">בן חסד בן ישר</addName>
                        <addName xml:id="ep-he" type="epithet"/>
                        <addName xml:id="ac-he" type="acronym"/>
                        <addName xml:id="sh-he" type="shuhra"/>
                    </persName><persName corresp="" type="canon" xml:lang="he-Latn" xml:id="name-9">
                        <forename ref="#fn-he" xml:lang="he-Latn">Yašar</forename>
                        <addName ref="#pa-he" type="patronym">ben Ḥesed ben Yašar</addName>
                        <addName ref="#ep-he" type="epithet"/>
                        <addName ref="#ac-he" type="acronym"/>
                        
                    </persName>
                    
                    
                    <birth>
                        <date cert="medium">1020-1030</date>
                        <placeName ref="" cert=""/>
                    </birth>
                    <death>
                        <date cert="medium">1097-1100</date>
                        <placeName ref="https://jalit.org/place/3">Jerusalem</placeName>
                    </death>
                    <floruit>
                        <date cert="high">1045-1095</date>
                        <placeName ref="https://jalit.org/place/3" cert="high">Jerusalem</placeName>
                        <placeName ref="https://jalit.org/place/1" cert="medium">Cairo</placeName>
                    </floruit>
                    <sex cert="">Male</sex>
                    <faith cert="">Karaite</faith>
                    <occupation type="" cert=""/>
                    <residence>
                        <placeName ref="https://jalit.org/place/3" cert="high">Jerusalem</placeName>
                    </residence>
                    <bibl type="bibliography" xml:id="jalit-orgbiblI85EL738">
                        <title>“Sahl b. al-Faḍl al-Tustarī’s Kitāb al-Īmāʾ.”</title>
                        <ptr target="https://jalit.org/bibl/I85EL738"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl type="bibliography" xml:id="jalit-orgbibl28U86NN">
                        <title>Gil, Moshe. “Tustari, Sahl b. al-Fadl al-.” In Jews in Islamic countries in the Middle Ages, (Leiden: Brill, 2004), pp. 269-271 [164].</title>
                        <ptr target="https://jalit.org/bibl/28U86NN"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl type="bibliography" xml:id="jalit-orgbiblGJ676VGP">
                        <title>Mann, Jacob. “Tustari, Sahl b. al-Fadl al-.” In Texts and Studies in Jewish History and Literature Karaitica, 2, (Philadelphia: Hebrew Press; Jewish Publication Society, 1935), pp. 39-40; 99; 100.</title>
                        <ptr target="https://jalit.org/bibl/GJ676VGP"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl type="bibliography" xml:id="jalit-orgbiblRVXRCIR3">
                        <title>Nemoy, Leon. “Tustari, Sahl b. al-Fadl al-.” In Karaite anthology: excerpts from the early literature, translated from Arabic, Aramaic, and Hebrew sources, (New Haven &amp; London: Yale University Press, 1952), pp. 230-235; 377.</title>
                        <ptr target="https://jalit.org/bibl/RVXRCIR3"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl type="bibliography" xml:id="jalit-orgbiblEFVRVADD">
                        <title>Poznański, Samuel Abraham. “The Karaite Literary Opponents of Saadiah Gaon in the Eleventh Century.” Jewish Quarterly Review 18 (1906): pp. 59-83. doi: https://doi.org/10.2307/1451104.</title>
                        <ptr target="https://jalit.org/bibl/EFVRVADD"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl type="bibliography" xml:id="jalit-orgbibl5MCRV2">
                        <title>Poznański, Samuel Abraham. “Tustari, Sahl b al-Fadl al-.” In Karaite studies, edited by Philip Birnbaum. (New York: Hermon Press, 1971), pp. 183-185.</title>
                        <ptr target="https://jalit.org/bibl/5MCRV2"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl type="bibliography" xml:id="jalit-orgbiblVF3ZU">
                        <title>Steinschneider, Moritz. “Tustari, Sahl b. al-Fadl al-.” In Die arabische Literatur der Juden Ein Beitrag zur Literaturgeschichte der Araber, grossenteils aus handschriftlichen Quellen, (Frankfurt am Main: J. Kauffmann, 1902), pp. 113 [69]; 342 [113].</title>
                        <ptr target="https://jalit.org/bibl/VF3ZU"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl type="bibliography" xml:id="jalit-orgbibl28L6BPW">
                        <title>Zawanowska, Marzena. “Sahl ibn Faḍl al-Tustarī.” Encyclopedia of Jews in the Islamic World, edited by Norman A. Stillman (Brill, 2010) https://referenceworks.brillonline.com/entries/encyclopedia-of-jews-in-the-islamic-world/sahl-ibn-fadl-al-tustari-SIM_0021740.</title>
                        <ptr target="https://jalit.org/bibl/28L6BPW"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl type="bibliography" xml:id="jalit-orgbiblWJRLN8T">
                        <title>בן-שמאי, חגי. “ישועה בן יהודה: לדמותו של חכם קראי ירושלמי במאה היא.” פעמים 32 (1987): pp. 6-5.</title>
                        <ptr target="https://jalit.org/bibl/WJRLN8T"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl type="bibliography" xml:id="jalit-orgbiblSVPXRV7K">
                        <title>גיל, משה. “Tustari, Sahl b. al-Fadl al-.” In התסתרים: המשפחה והכת, (תל אביב: המכון לחקר התפוצות, 1981), pp. 65-63.</title>
                        <ptr target="https://jalit.org/bibl/SVPXRV7K"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <idno type="URI" subtype="isni"/>
                    <idno type="URI" subtype="viaf">http://viaf.org/viaf/82146461459227730116</idno>
                    <idno type="URI" subtype="wiki"/>
                    <idno type="URI" subtype="gnd"/>
                    <idno type="URI" subtype="merhav"/>
                    <idno type="URI" subtype="rambi"/>
                    <idno type="URI" subtype="imhm"/>
                    <idno type="URI" subtype="ktiv"/>
                </person>
            </listPerson>
        </body>
    </text>
    <standOff>
        <list>
            <item>
                <note xml:lang="en"><p>Samuel Abraham Poznański (1864–1921) was a scholar of Polish-Jewish descent, renowned for his research on Karaism and the Hebrew calendar. He was a pioneer in Judeo-Arabic studies, a Hebrew bibliographer, and a recognized authority on contemporary and historic Qaraism. Additionally, he served as a rabbi at the Great Synagogue in Warsaw. </p><p> Poznański harbored a profound aspiration to compile a biographical dictionary of Qaraite scholars and a historical dictionary of Qaraite literature, considering them the apex of his scholarly endeavors. Unfortunately, his sudden demise thwarted the 
<lb/> realization of these ambitions, and he only managed to publish a limited number of bibliographical essays on the subject. The draft of his <emph rend="italic"> Encyclopedia of Qaraites </emph> is today found in the Samuel Poznański Archive at the National Library of Israel (ARC 4﹡ 1180, Series 5). Given the current condition of the archive, referencing specific pages or files is not feasible. The entries are primarily organized by first names. </p><p> Provided by a cooperation between the Ben Zvi Institute, Jerusalem, and LMU, Munich, used according to CC BY NC 4.0 (Associate researcher: Amir Mazor) </p><p> Literature: 
<lb/> Miriam Frenkel, “Samuel Abraham Poznański’s Karaite Mission: From Wissenschaft to Jewish Nationalism,” in <emph rend="italic"> Modern Jewish Scholarship on Islam in Context: Rationality, European Borders, and the Search for Belonging </emph> , edited by Ottfried Fraisse (Berlin: De Gruyter, 2019), pp. 121–144 [134].</p></note>
                <persName/>
                <quote xml:lang="he"><p>ישר בן חסד בן ישר </p><p> ובערבית אבו פצ'ל סהל בן פצ'ל בן סהל אלתסתרי (או אלדסתרי), אחד מן המחברים הנכבדים והקדומים אבל עד העת האחרונה כמעט שלא נודע שום דבר אודותיו. כינויו אלדסתרי מורה על תסתר בארץ פרס, אבל כנראה משם היה רק מקור משפחתו ואולם הוא גר בודאי בקהיר, כי מצאנו שם את אביו חסד (ע"ע). את זמנו נוכל להוכיח מזה כי עלי בן סלימאן באחד מחיבוריו שחיבר בשנת תס"ה להג'רה (=1072/3) מביאו בתור בן דורו הגדול ממנו בשנים, אבל בברכת החיים (אדאם אללה בקאה). מלבד זה מובא עוד על ידי שלשה מחברים: מאת מלמד פאצ'ל בסדורו שמכנה אותו ישר בן חסדאל בן ישר אלתסתרי, בחלוק הקראים והרבנים (רשימת ליידן 389, ל"ק 106) שמכנה אותו ישר בן חסד, ומאת אבן אלהיתי אשר מסר לנו על אודותיו ידיעות נכבדות מאד (JQR IX:435) וזה לשונו: "ואלשיך' ישר בן חסד בן ישר אלדסתרי רח' א'ת' כאן מן אלעלמא אלכבאר ולה כתאב אלתלויח פי עלם אלכלאם פי אלפאצ'הם ובראהינהם ורד עלי אלפיומי איצ'א ולה כתאב פי אלאעתדאל וכתב כת'ירא מן אלפקה אלמדכ'ל." ובעברית: "והזקן ישר בן חסד בן ישר הדסתרי יר' אל היה מן המלומדים הגדולים וחיבר ספר ההערות על חכמת הדבור במה שנוגע לביטוייהם ולראיותיהם והשיג גם כן על הפיומי (ר"ל רס"ג) ועוד לו חיבור על השיווי (?) והרבה חיבורים על אופני ההלכה". הנה אם כן חיבר ישר חיבורים בפילוסופיה ובהלכה וחוץ מזה השיב על רס"ג אם בחיבור בפני עצמו או באחד מחיבוריו, אבל לבד מזה כתב עוד חיבורים שלא נזכרו אצל אבן אלהיתי. כן יימצא חלק מפירושו על התורה בערבית בכ"י בפטרסבורג (הרכבי ב-ZATW I:158) ונראה כי השתמש בו בעל פירוש ערבי לדברים שנתחבר בשנת קי"ב (כ"י בר' מוז' 334) כי מביא בו בין שאר המחברים ודבריהם גם "כלאם אלדסתרי", וכ"י בר' מוז' 8965 (דף כ'-ס"ז) מכיל (באותיות ערביות) קצורים מן שני ספרי ישר בפילוסופיה, היינו מן כתאב אלתלויח הנ"ל (שמכונה פה בכינוי משונה מעט) ועוד מן ספר שהיה כולל הערות ביקורתיות לספרו של אריסטו על מה שאחר הטבע "מואצ'ע מתפרעה מן כתאב אלשיך' אלג'ליל אבי אלפצ'ל סהל בן אלפצ'ל בן סהל אלתסתרי אדאם אללה עלאה (ואם כן נכתב עוד בחיי המחבר) מן כתאבה אלמוסום באלתלויח אלי אלתוחיד ואלעדל ומואצ'ע מן כתאבה אלמוסום באלתחריר לכתאב אריסטו פימא בעד אלטביעה." מהספר הראשון יש כתובות של פרקים אלו: פי . . . מן את'באת קדים; פי את'באת אלקדים סבחאנה קאדרא; באב פי את'באתה סבחאנה עאלמא. ומן הספר השני יש הערות להמאמר השלישי של ספר אריסטו (מן אלמקאלה אלת'אלת'ה מן אלכתאב תחריר . אלכלאם פי אלמוגוד הל הו . . . פי ג'מיע אלמוג'ודאת); להמאמר הששי (מן תחריראת אלמקאלה אלסאדסה); להמאמר השביעי (מן אלמקאלה אלסאבעה מן אלכתאב, כלאם ארסטו. פאמא . . . אלג'והר לטביעיה אלא אנהא מובדה אלך'); ולמאמר י"א (מן אלמקאלה אלחאדיה עשר והי אלמוסומה במקאלה אלכלאם, תחריר. לקאיל אן יקול אנא אן אלחרכה . . . עלי אלאטלאק אלך'). והנה ראינו כי שם הספר הראשון היה "הערות על דבר היחוד והצדק" והם חיבור שני מלות רגילות אצל המדברים ומי יודע אם איננו אחד עם "כתאב אלאשארה פי אצול אלתוחיד ואלעדל" שנזכר ברשימה בראש כ"י בר' מוז' 589 עי' רשימת מרגליות ח"ב 180a. </p><p> בזכרון לראשונים ח' מביא הרכבי דבר מספר מצות ערבי שבאו בו דברי ענן במקורם הארמי ועל כמה מהם הנוגעים לדיני טומאה וטהרה ולדיני מילה. הוא אומר שאפשר שהם מחיבורו של ישר, עי' עמ' 65 הערה ד', 66 ע' ה', 75 ע' א' (וזה הולך עד עמ' 89) והוא כנראה אותו חיבור שמובא גם בעמ' 187 הערה ו' והוא באסיפה שניה 717 ושם יסתפק אם הוא מישר או מעלי בן סלימאן. [סהל בן פצ'ל </p><p> ביבליוגרפיה: </p><p> גוטלובר, בקרת, 186; [גיל, משה, התסתרים: המשפחה והכת, תל אביב, 1981;] </p><p> Poznanski, MGWJ 41:189; idem, Zur jud.-ar. Literatur, 15, 59; idem, KLO, no. 18; idem, REJ 65:156; idem, Schwan Festschrift, 477-478; Steinschneider, JQR 12:124; idem, Ar. Lit., sec. 69; G. Margoliouth, REJ 57:314; ]</p></quote>
                <bibl xml:id="jalit-orgbiblDJV65BQJ">
                    <title>Samuel Abraham Poznański, Encyclopedia of Qaraites (Jerusalem, n.d.), אנציקלופדיה בני מקרא, The National Library of Israel: Samuel Poznanski Archive, ARC 4﹡ 1180, Series 5, https://www.nli.org.il/he/archives/NNL\ARCHIVE\AL990032439840205171/NLI.</title>
                    <ptr target="https://jalit.org/bibl/DJV65BQJ"/>
                </bibl>
            </item>
        </list>
    </standOff>
</TEI>
